600 to dispatch,
what you got running on this, go on?
To 600,
we haven't been able to
dispatch anybody yet.
Six oh one to dispatch.
Six oh one establish
command at 6th and Harvey.
On April 19th, 1995,
as many people were
starting their workday,
a beautiful spring morning
in the heartland became chaos
when at 9:02 A.M., explosions tore through
the Alfred p. Murrah federal building
in downtown Oklahoma city.
An explosion at
nine o'clock this morning
that did that damage you're
looking at right there,
blowing off the entire
north face of that building.
- The federal building located
200 north west 5th street
was almost completely destroyed.
- A terrible tragedy has
occurred here in Oklahoma city.
- The bombing in Oklahoma city
was an attack on innocent children,
and defenseless citizens.
168 people were killed
in the blast and over 800 wounded.
The hospitals were
overrun with casualties.
A rescue worker was
killed from falling debris
within the first few hours.
But what would sear the bombing
in the hearts of Americans
was the 19 children
inside the daycare center in the building
who had lost their lives.
The most beautiful
memorial left by anyone
is not in the rubble of this building,
but in the hearts and
the lives that knew them
and loved them.
We come today to remember their lives,
and we come today to offer thanks.
Thanks for the hundreds
and hundreds of people
who were involved in the
rescue and recovery efforts.
Six years before 9/11,
it was the first mass casualty
terrorist attack on American soil.
The prologue to a new
chapter in American history
had been written in
blood, fear, and shock.
Terrorism had struck home.
From now on, nothing
would be the same again.
- We know that more than McVeigh
and Nichols were involved.
- There were questions of other bombs
being found at the scene of the crime,
witnesses to the bombing.
- The FBI, like any government agency,
is more concerned with power, prestige,
maintaining its position,
rather than truth and justice.
- Based on the damage
pattern to the building,
what the government said is impossible.
- That life we had back
before the bombing,
that life is over.
- For the first time in my
fight with the government,
they stepped forward and said,
"it would pose a grave risk
to the national security
of the United States of America
if we release these CIA documents."
- If you know the truth,
the truth will set you free.
- You've got to band together
or it's over for all of us.
The man on top will get you.
- If we don't expose the facts
that Oklahoma city stinks to high heaven,
the same people that carried it out
are going to do it over,
and over, and over again.
And they're going to use
these frightening events
to drive a stake through the United States
and kill our republic.
Almost immediately
the Oklahoma city police department
announced a "be on the lookout" alert
for two middle eastern looking suspects
wearing blue jogging suits.
Shortly before the bombing,
they were seen by a witness
running from the murrah building
and getting into a brown pickup truck,
then driving away from
the scene of the crime.
It was soon determined that a truck bomb
had exploded directly
outside the building.
Approximately 200 feet
from the bomb crater,
a vin number, stamped on a twisted axle,
identified the vehicle
as a Ryder rental truck.
- Two suspects are in custody
this evening in the bombing
of Oklahoma city's
murrah federal building.
Shortly after the bombing,
a 26 year old U.S. army veteran,
Timothy McVeigh, was pulled over by
an Oklahoma highway patrol officer,
60 miles north of Oklahoma city.
He was stopped for speeding in his car
without a license plate.
McVeigh would admit to
carrying a concealed handgun,
and was taken into
custody without incident.
It was the first time Timothy McVeigh
had been arrested in his life.
The original alert for
two middle eastern males
had been rescinded within
hours of the bombing.
And the identification
number on the Ryder axle
was traced to a rental agency in Kansas.
The renter had given a false name,
but had listed his address as a farmhouse
in Michigan belonging to James Nichols.
James's brother Terry Nichols
was a friend of Tim McVeigh
from their time in the U.S. army.
Upon hearing the news that he was wanted
for questioning in the bombing,
Terry Nichols turned himself
in to the harrington,
Kansas police department.
Within 24 hours after the attack,
the FBI had received a
tip from a former coworker
of Tim McVeigh in buffalo, New York.
The tipster informed the FBI that McVeigh
had often espoused militant
antigovernment views
and that McVeigh was very angry
over the siege of the branch davidians
by federal agents in waco, Texas,
which had ended in a catastrophic fire
two years to the day before
the Oklahoma city bombing.
- That Friday they showed
the FBI bringing Tim McVeigh
out of the jail in Perry, Oklahoma.
And that's when I got angry.
When I saw that it was an American
and it wasn't middle easterners.
I had a hard time accepting the fact
that Americans would do that.
Americans are supposed
to love their children.
They're not supposed to
murder their children.
- Shaken, disillusioned, angered
that that could happen in this country.
Upon learning that
McVeigh was already in jail,
the FBI transferred him to federal custody
and an indictment was
issued against Tim McVeigh,
Terry Nichols, and others unknown
for the bombing of the
murrah federal building.
Another army buddy of McVeigh's,
Michael fortier of Kingman, Arizona,
was later arrested and charged
with having advanced
knowledge of the bombing plot.
- The last thing I
remember was being thrown
to the center of that room and looking up
and looking into the sky,
and there was no roof
and everything was just
suspended up in the air,
in the sky.
- When I came to, I stood
up facing the south,
but all the light was behind me.
I turned, looked back to the north
and the whole front of
the building's gone.
I'm about, oh, four to five
feet from where it dropped off.
- On the morning of April 19th,
1995, my dog, gunny and I,
arrived at the scene
of the murrah building.
There was a great deal
of chaos at the scene.
A lot of people bleeding,
screaming, running away from the building.
- I lost my two grandchildren.
They were in the daycare
center at the murrah building.
Their names were Aaron
and Elijah Coverdale.
Aaron was five years old.
Elijah was two.
I was living at the regency
when the bombing happened.
That morning I was at work.
I had custody of Aaron and Elijah
so they lived with me.
And I had dropped them
off at the daycare center
that Wednesday morning.
I'd get up in the middle of
the night and get in the shower
and turn the water on so people
wouldn't hear me screaming.
And I'd just scream at god
and ask him, "what was wrong?
Why were we being punished so?"
- I knew the Coverdale
boys, Elijah and Aaron.
These two boys, they were characters.
Me being single and
living in this apartment,
I was kind of a party guy
at that time, 27 years old.
At one point in time, I
had promised these two boys
that I was gonna give them some toys.
And problem with that,
living in the regency,
you know, 18th floor, you
leave something in your car,
you don't wanna go back down and get it
because it's just a hassle
unless it's ice cream.
And so, I left these toys in
the car for the longest time.
And I never did get them
those toys until, you know,
after they passed away,
when I gave them to jannie.
- Well, I got watching the
stuff down on the street.
I kinda got mesmerized by what
was going on down on the street.
While I was standing up
there, there was a little girl
that was taking a photography class at uco
that took a picture of the building
and I was in that picture.
- You could not see
anything in front of you.
It was so, the smoke was
so thick and so Black.
And the only thing I can tell
you is it smelled like sulfur.
If you were in a chemistry
lab, it smelled like sulfur.
And she said, "you can't go that way."
And I said, "why?"
She said, "there is nothing out there.
It's gone."
The reasons for
the bombing, the perpetrators,
the rumors, and the suspects change
depending on whose viewpoint you take.
Like all controversial events,
some of those closest to the event,
and farthest away, are bound together
by their questioning
of the official story.
The first questions were directed
at the bureau of alcohol,
tobacco, and firearms
which had launched the raid
on the branch davidians.
The Oklahoma city office for the atf
was located in the murrah building,
and was the supposed target of the attack.
Yet, no agents were killed
or seriously wounded.
Was the atf office empty that morning?
- I'm asking if I can
speak with an atf officer
that worked in the building
so I could find out
if they knew anything about my wife
and he told me that they were
in debriefing and I asked him,
you know, "I need to talk to one of 'em.
I need to find out something."
And he said that none of them
had been in the building,
so they weren't hurt.
They had been tipped by their pagers
that morning not to come into work.
The atf told
several different stories
to explain their agents' curious absences.
The most fantastic story
was that two agents
were indeed inside the building
and were heroes that day.
Atf agent Luke franey claimed
that he was knocked unconscious
by the blast and after an
aborted helicopter rescue,
crawled onto an outside
ledge to escape his office.
Franey reported that he then
used his martial arts skills
to break through several
walls and injured his hand.
Another agent, Alex mccauley,
claimed that he was in an elevator
at the time of the bombing.
After free falling for five floors,
mccauley supposedly broke out
and rescued several people.
- My crews were the crews
working on the murrah building
the day of the bombing.
Immediately after the bombing,
they called me on the radios
and at that point they were
going in to assist with,
because the fire department
hadn't even got there yet.
They were going to check to make sure
all the elevators were clear.
They weren't aware,
because they were coming
from the south side,
that the building on
the north side was gone.
So they went in to check the
elevators and that's when
they found out how bad the
damage was inside the building.
None of the elevators went to free fall
because the governor
overspeeds were not tripped.
The safety mechanisms on
the bottom of the elevators
were not tripped,
none of the elevators had
a free fall condition.
I think it was mccauley indicated
that they were trapped in an elevator,
so at the grand jury investigation,
once I got the fema report that showed
which elevator they were in,
I said that there's no possible way
they could've been in that elevator
because my men checked it
and it was still locked
from the top and the doors were,
the wall had caved in against
the doors between floors,
so they couldn't have gotten out
of the elevator without assistance.
Jane Graham
worked in the building
for over a decade,
was vice president of the
federal employees union,
and has testified before
congress on labor issues.
She knew everyone in the building,
and bore witness to suspicious
behavior that morning.
- On the morning of the bombing,
when my husband dropped me
off and I got out of the car,
as I was walking toward the entrance,
there were two men standing
directly in front of the double doors,
and there was a little sitting area there,
planter and so forth there in front.
They were standing right
there on the sidewalk.
They had on atf jackets
which said, "atf" on them.
They were talking to a third gentleman
who was dressed in business clothes.
And I saw them.
Their backs were to me and I thought,
they don't normally, you know,
all of the people we
see go up there to atf,
they're never identifiable.
You know, they always
are dressed, you know,
a lot of 'em look like drug
people and other things.
You know, but they're
certainly not dressed
for you to be able to tell who they are.
A paramedic who responded
to the bombing, Tiffany Bible,
confirms that the atf
were not in their office,
and, in fact, may have been aware
of some type of threat that day.
In this affidavit,
she states that immediately
after the bombing,
she asked an atf agent on the scene
if any of them were in the building.
He responded, "no, we
weren't in there today."
And that "the murrah building
was bombed because of waco."
She further states
that within the first 20
minutes of the bombing,
she saw at least 8 atf agents
outside the building in
clean, Black jumpsuits.
To this day the atf has been unwilling
to address their prior
knowledge of the bombing.
Beyond the vague rumors of the
significance of April 19th,
some federal agencies were
aware of an actual threat.
- One of the most frustrating
things about prior knowledge
is that the media, some in the media,
and others would accuse us of saying
that the government blew the building up.
Which we never said.
And I do not believe.
The U.S. marshals,
responsible for security
of federal personnel and facilities,
warned that, quote, "islamic terrorists
may be planning suicide attacks
against federal courthouses
and government installations
designed to attract
worldwide press attention
through the murder of innocent victims."
The atf had placed informant Carol howe
into a white separatist community
in eastern Oklahoma called elhoim city
another atf agent admitted
under oath that one suspect,
Andy strassmeir, was
reported to make, quote,
"threats to blow up federal
buildings", unquote,
before the Oklahoma city bombing.
Furthermore, Carol howe actually drove
strassmeir and other suspects
to Oklahoma city to scout bombing targets.
Was this the source of the
atf suspicious behavior
the morning of April 19th?
U.S. representative Ernest
istook, of Oklahoma,
also displayed advanced
knowledge of the bombing.
- To my left, from the east,
I saw senator istook
kinda work his way west.
Well, he came up to me and we
started talking small talk.
You know, terrible thing and all this,
and really didn't know what much to say.
And he said, all of sudden
he made the comment,
"yeah, we knew this was gonna happen."
- I noticed the lady back behind me
by a backhoe over there taking pictures.
She identified herself as an
attorney, Lanny, Lana Tyree,
and she was with Ernest istook.
And she made a comment to
me that istook told her
that they were aware of a
bomb threat since April 9th.
We didn't really think much
about it until this grand jury
started probing into it
and people were claiming
that there wasn't any prior knowledge.
But, you know, I start thinking
about it and got with Dave,
and we put two and two together,
and we said, "hey, somebody
knew about a prior bomb threat.
You know, this ought to be known."
- Everyone who knows me
knows I would not sit idle
if I knew about a conspiracy of silence.
I would never rest until such
a conspiracy was exposed.
But I know of no such conspiracy.
Istook has denied
this evidence under oath,
but he has never answered
the Oklahoma county
sheriff's deputy's challenge
to subject his opposing
versions of prior knowledge
to polygraph testing.
Many witnesses have officially stated
that the Oklahoma county bomb
squad was conducting a search
at the federal courthouse
across the street
from the murrah building
two hours before the attack.
- Trish nix, I ran into her.
She was another employee there at hud.
And she had asked me if I had seen
the bomb squad that morning.
And I had said, "no, I wasn't aware
that they had been in the building."
And she said, "yes."
She had seen their unit
parked in the parking lot
of the church across the street.
County appraiser j.D. Reed
saw the bomb disposal unit
parked outside the
courthouse that morning.
Despite multiple eyewitnesses,
the sheriff's department
denies this claim.
- If that building was under threat,
and they were getting bomb threats,
and this was a daily
thing, or a weekly thing,
or if they've gotten many
threats, or only one,
the parents of the
children in that daycare
deserved to have been notified.
People do not keep children in daycares
where there are bomb threats made.
Under the
pressure of mounting evidence,
abc's "20/20" reported on many
of these puzzling questions
a year and a half after the bombing.
- At issue, increasingly,
for some of the victims
and their families,
what did authorities know or
suspect before the explosion,
that federal workers and the children
arriving at the murrah building
did not know or were not told?
There was this fairly large truck
with a trailer behind it
and it had a shield on
the side of the door,
and it said, "bomb disposal"
or "bomb squad" below it.
Authorities now claim,
in federal investigative reports,
that the huge ominous
truck with its trailer,
was being used by a deputy
to run routine errands.
Other documents obtained by
"20/20" show that someone called
the executive secretariat's office
at the justice department
in Washington and said,
"the murrah building had been bombed."
But this was 24 minutes before the blast.
No action was apparently taken.
According
to the show's producer
the justice department
actively intervened to prevent
an in-depth follow up to this segment
from airing nationally.
- "20/20" did a 15 or 20 minute
segment on prior knowledge.
It was put together by a
guy named Roger Charles.
That was so explosive that
he was putting together
an entire hour or whatever for "20/20",
which he would tell you.
But the feds came in and stopped "20/20."
Wouldn't let them broadcast
the larger segment
that he put together
concerning prior knowledge.
- The news channel has learned
of another strange development.
Apparently before the bombing,
governor frank keating's brother Mark
had been working on a novel
about a terrorist
bombing in Oklahoma city.
Stranger still, one of the
characters in the novel
was named Thomas McVeigh.
Despite the official denials,
the evidence confirms
that at least some amount
of prior knowledge existed.
More ominously, there are suggestions
that certain government agencies
were fully expecting a
bombing to occur that day.
- The horse patrol, interestingly,
was a very small unit, and was assisted
by the county reserve mounted patrol unit.
For whatever reason, on
the morning of the bombing,
they had been assigned and had already met
at the Oklahoma city
equine and canine facility.
And had prepared their horses, their tack,
and uniforms to go
downtown for crowd control.
Rarely, very rarely would
they go down and patrol
or work the downtown area for
crowd control, for anything.
The importance
of exposing prior knowledge
cannot be understated.
Those individuals who
understood the danger beforehand
and did nothing are just as guilty
as those who lit the fuse on the bomb.
As the FBI and department of justice
narrowed its focus on Tim McVeigh
as the lone bomber on April 19th,
people seeking truth and justice
for the dead were dismayed
that so many reports of accomplices
were being discarded by
the federal authorities.
The first sketches of the
suspects released by the FBI
clearly indicated that
two people were involved
in parking the Ryder truck in
front of the murrah building.
And the original bola, or
"be on the lookout alert"
had mentioned three suspects.
When the hunt for John
Doe #2 was called off
and he was dismissed as a ghost,
people who knew for a fact
that they had seen
McVeigh with other people,
began to speak out.
Did McVeigh act alone?
- During that time
broadcasts were being made
that there was suspects had been observed
leaving the scene in a brown pickup.
- At this time people were
trying to get together
on who was going to do what,
medical personnel and such.
There was a police car sitting to my left
facing west on 5th street
and as we were all standing
there, conversing, and you know,
people were doing what they were doing,
it came out over the
radio on this police car,
that they were looking for a brown truck.
An apb for a brown truck.
It was quick.
But it was heard.
- I haven't stopped asking questions,
because I know that we
haven't been told the truth.
I've talked to too many people
that saw Timothy McVeigh that morning,
saw Timothy McVeigh in Kansas,
and saw Timothy McVeigh in Oklahoma city.
Not one person saw him by himself.
- Timothy McVeigh
stepped out of the truck.
I walked him over to,
let's say 10, 11 feet away
from the truck itself.
I pointed a direction
downtown, which is to my right.
He seemed to acknowledge
where I was talking about.
At that time, the gentleman
walked back to the truck.
I talked to him, I also noticed
there was a passenger in
the truck at that time.
- And mostly it was a John Doe two thing,
because you remember,
it was the greatest
manhunt there's ever been.
And then all of a sudden,
"hey, he doesn't even exist."
If he doesn't exist, what was
the deal about the manhunt?
I mean things like that.
That was continually coming out.
- I know for a fact Timothy McVeigh
was with another individual
on the morning of April 19th
right before the bombing.
- Because the evidence is
overwhelming and compelling
that there were other perpetrators,
and they were not pursued.
In the very early days after the bombing
the decision was made not to pursue
any more of those individuals.
In the days
before the bombing Tim McVeigh
was seen making preparations
with other suspects.
Not Terry Nichols, or Michael fortier,
but others unknown,
whom the authorities seemed
uninterested in finding.
- The man that I saw
on the phone that day,
that was actually on
the phone was McVeigh.
I'm 100% sure of that.
He had a partner with him
that had shoulder-length hair,
that was leaned up against
the wall facing him.
Then at one point he turned
to the guy to his right,
who was leaning against the
wall, shoulder-length hair,
and said, "he told us
to stay here."
I did go up to the FBI at 50 penn place
and told them my story.
If I remember right,
I think they actually
sketched out the second person
that I was describing,
which was shoulder-length
hair, tan, stocky build,
a light plaid type jacket shirt kinda mix,
kinda goofy looking guy.
A convenience
store clerk reported to the FBI
that McVeigh had purchased
fuel for a Ryder truck
at her store two days before the bombing,
even pointing out on the register tape
when the purchase was made.
Accompanying McVeigh was another suspect.
This example is only one
of many eyewitness accounts
that diverge from the official narrative.
And although the government states
that McVeigh never scouted
inside the murrah building,
a secret service investigator
reported that she had seen him
in the building, also
with a second suspect.
The official narrative
dictates that Tim McVeigh alone
rented the Ryder truck
in junction city, Kansas
on April 17, two days before the bombing.
He and Terry Nichols
supposedly constructed the bomb
on April 18th.
But the bulk of eyewitness accounts assert
that the Ryder truck was at geary lake
for several days before that.
- I retired April 11, 1995
and after finishing up that morning,
I decided to stop by here
and fish at geary state lake,
which is right in this general area here
that I was fishing from,
the pier, or jetty.
And I stayed here most
of the afternoon fishing,
of course with no luck.
And later on that afternoon
I had decided to maybe go
back over this way over here
to the other point back there
and see if I'd have any luck.
When I noticed a Ryder truck over there.
I was sitting at home one day
and my wife came in from work
and she said that she had been stopped
at a Road block up here
at geary lake in reference
to the Oklahoma city bombing.
And the making of the bomb here
at geary state lake with a Ryder truck.
And I said, "well, you
know, I had told you
about the Ryder truck I had
seen there before this."
And that's how I became aware of it.
And then the next thing I
knew, she told the atf and FBI,
the people at the
roadblock, what I had seen.
And before I knew it, my
house was swarming with
agents.
McVeigh stayed
at the dreamland motel
just outside the gates
of fort Riley, Kansas
while he rented the
truck and built the bomb.
Once again, eyewitnesses
state that he was not alone
and the Ryder truck was there for days
before the FBI insists it was.
The maid at the dreamland
saw McVeigh's friend with the Ryder truck,
and when shown a sketch of
John Doe #2, told the FBI,
"my god, who did the sketch?
It looks just like him."
All these reports indicate
that more than one Ryder truck
was involved in the bombing,
and more people than the
government is letting on.
- Justice for these
killers will be certain,
swift, and severe.
We will find them, we will convict them,
and we will seek the
death penalty for them.
It was promised to the people
of Oklahoma city and
to the rest of america
that every single person
responsible for the bombing
would be caught, tried,
and held accountable
for the harm they had inflicted.
It was expected that this promise
would be fulfilled.
Nevertheless, as eyewitness testimony
and other promising leads were being
carelessly discarded,
replaced only with the lies
and inconsistencies of federal officials,
a deep but private suspicion
grew in the minds of observers
that perhaps a government cover-up
was underway.
Was this mere incompetence
or was there something else
at work here?
- I was a police officer in
the Tulsa police department
for 27 years, and in 1995,
when the Oklahoma city bombing occurred,
I was requested by the local FBI office
through our chief of police to assist
any way I could and look into the bombing
and using my contacts as an
investigative journalist,
which is what I did on the
side, to try to find out
anything we could find
out about the bombing:
McVeigh, Nichols, and just kind of follow
the investigation anyplace it went.
Just follow the leads.
I was still working the case with
jayna Davis and David Hoffman,
two Oklahoma city police officers.
And one of 'em, it was
one of the first ones
in the building, and he saw some things
in the building, he saw the biggest damage
to the building was the pit,
which was in the back of the building
and went down, like, two or three floors.
He saw all of that.
That never came out in the news.
It wasn't part of the investigation.
It didn't count.
In other words, if it didn't fit the mold
that the department of
justice under Janet Reno set
for the FBI, then it
wasn't put in the case.
Period.
The FBI
bragged about its handling
of the deadliest terror
attack in American history,
but gigantic holes in the
case were being ignored
by the media.
McVeigh was first suspected
because he rented the truck
under the name Robert kling.
One of the first pieces of evidence used
to link McVeigh to the
bombing was problematic.
- I went to junction city.
I went out to Elliott's body shop
and I spoke to Mr. Elliott.
I told him who I was, and I said,
"I would like for you to tell me
what happened the day Tim came to rent
the Ryder truck."
And he said, "you mean, the
day Tim and his friend came?"
And I said, "Tim wasn't by himself?"
He said, "no, ma'am."
- The FBI had been designated
by President Clinton
as the lead federal agency
in this investigation.
Incredibly enough, there remains
an extra unidentified leg
that was found in the rubble.
Oklahoma state medical
examiner Fred Jordan
testified in court, "we had eight people
with traumatically amputated left legs.
However, we have nine left legs.
We have one leg too many."
Stephen Jones, McVeigh's defense attorney,
detailed in his book, "others unknown,"
the significance of this extra leg.
Former chief pathologist
for northern Ireland,
t.k. Marshall, performed
over 2,500 autopsies
on bombing victims, and told Jones that,
"in all the years in Ireland,
we identified every innocent person
that was killed.
There was never an unknown victim."
The FBI collected 1,034 fingerprints
during their investigation, but
an agent admitted under oath
that these prints were not run through
the national fingerprint database.
Niki deutchman was the jury foreperson
for the federal trial of Terry Nichols.
- I think that the government, perhaps,
really dropped the ball.
I think that there were a
large number of sightings
right around before,
the week before and the days and months
after the bombing.
And sketches of people
that were recognizable.
In this trial, there even was a photograph
of someone who may have been involved
with mixing the bomb, with
putting the bomb together.
And that person, it was a photograph
from the newspaper, obviously,
that person's identity is known.
I think there are other people out there
and decisions were
probably made very early on
that Tim McVeigh and Terry Nichols
were who they were looking for
and the same sort of
resources were not used
to try to find out who
else might be involved.
- Well, in those first couple of days,
especially that first day of
the Oklahoma city bombing,
there was immediate
information that came out
about what caused the bombing,
witnesses on the scene of the crime,
things such as that, and it changed
very significantly and drastically
as the day went by and the
next several days went by.
That caused a lot of
questions in people's minds
about what really happened here.
- The reason I doubt, started doubting
the official story that was comin' out,
you have to understand that the state,
the local media were doing a good job
the first day.
Local law enforcement,
maybe, also, I believe,
was doing a good job.
But once the feds came in,
things started changing.
The police and emergency
crews are talking about
moving us back because of the danger of,
possibility of another explosion.
I think he
said, "another bomb."
Another bomb, move back.
- Oh, my god, another bomb.
- The fire crews and the
various emergency crews
are trying to get in, but
we keep getting reports
that there may be other
devices in the area.
They will use that
trailer, you see the bucket
on the back there, sort of, this is how
they would transport the explosive device
away from this populated area to try
to do something with it.
- There were two unexploded devices
discovered subsequently
in the initial explosion.
A second bomb was
found on the east side
of that building, a bomb
squad is on the scene.
That second bomb has not exploded.
We don't know quite the status yet.
If they've managed to diffuse
it, but it has been confirmed.
- There have been reports
of two explosive devices,
unexploded explosive devices.
Two different
explosive devices were found
in addition to the one that went off.
Just an hour after
the initial explosion,
downtown Oklahoma city
was shaken up again,
with word of another bomb, or maybe two.
- They've had to back off a couple times,
'cause they found, I guess,
two or three other bombs
or at least explosive devices down there
that they've had to diffuse.
- They shut down operation
for about 20, 30 minutes
because of that, and
that was very frustrating
'cause we were right at the point
where we had people and
we had to leave 'em.
The first bomb that
was in the federal building
did go off, it did the damage
that you see right there.
The second explosive
was found and diffused.
- The Oklahoma city bombing
was one of the first
big stories that I covered,
and it was just shocking to
know it was an inside job,
to know that the media was
involved in the cover-up.
And that the mainstream
television stations
there in Oklahoma city, knew
what had really happened,
and then years later,
I was able to actually
talk to some of those reporters,
and they discussed how
they were told to shut up.
I mean, it just showed
how people were so willing
to be part of the cover-up just because
the truth was so frightening.
And that's really why
we've become so enslaved,
is that we just give in to the lies,
and they start little, but
they get bigger and bigger.
- It's amazing when everyone
who can see an event
and that gets changed into something else,
simply because the media
presents it that way.
That means the media's
complicit in the cover-up.
They're not hapless.
They're not ignorant.
How come I can figure
this out and CNN can't?
- The controlled corporate
mainstream media is essential
to a cover-up like Oklahoma city
being successful, and that's why
the mainstream media has
lost so much credibility.
Because all over the nation,
people have seen things like Oklahoma city
over and over again, where
you see the live footage,
you see them removing the bombs,
you see the governor admitting it,
and then later, the media
says, "we never said that.
That's what conspiracy theorists say."
At first, the
media reported on some of these
bothersome pieces of evidence,
but they became little more than parrots
for the justice department
as the official story
was railroaded into the public mind.
- Been listening to Mike mccurry,
President Clinton spokesperson
at the white house.
Apparently, at this point,
we know a little bit more
than the white house does
because we have been able
to confirm that it was a car explosion.
Now that word coming to us
from mayor Ron norick earlier,
1,200 pounds of explosives parked out
in front of the federal building.
And atf has
confirmed that as well.
- Who's going to investigate
the investigators?
Who's going to investigate
the prosecutors?
Who's gonna hold them accountable?
Who's gonna hold us public
officials accountable?
And that's all we're trying to do here
among trying, in addition to trying
to find the truth.
- Well, initially, that morning,
all the media that was
downtown there reporting
were reporting the truth.
They reported the truth
about the unexploded bombs,
undetonated bombs being
removed from the building.
By afternoon, things began
to ease a little bit,
they're just, you could sense a difference
and by the next day,
everybody but channel 4
had changed their story completely.
One local station
in Oklahoma city, kfor-TV,
did perform its duty by
reporting McVeigh's accomplices,
the evidence of prior warnings,
and many other aspects of the case.
The New York times broadcasting company
purchased kfor a year after the bombing.
The programming director was fired,
the lead journalist on
the bombing, jayna Davis,
was let go, and all reporting
that contradicted the
government, banished.
The victims turned to the government
with their questions,
expecting the full truth
to come out.
This was not to be.
Those who asked too many
questions or knew too much
were discouraged from their
efforts in other ways.
- Debbie nakanashi, who
was with the post office,
she was told not to talk
to anybody about that.
Her job had been threatened to her,
she went to the union over it.
Then they apologized, but she and I went
on a number of occasions
to Washington, D.C.
We tried to see every senator
and every congressman from Oklahoma.
Not one would give us an interview.
- I was told by an agent, an FBI agent,
that the comments that I'd made, that,
people like me often ended up dead,
and be careful what I said
if I was him.
In the way that he put it forth,
I felt like it was a threat.
- I wrote letters to Janet Reno
when she was the united
states Attorney General.
I wrote Louis freeh, was was over the FBI
at that time, I wrote senator orrin hatch.
I wrote everybody I could think of
askin' for help.
Nothin' was done.
When the government decided
that the investigation
was over, a federal
grand jury was impaneled
to hand down indictments.
This is usually a straightforward process.
But the federal prosecutors
were not counting on
one grand juror, hoppy Heidelberg,
to actually ask questions of his own.
- My name is hoppy
Heidelberg and I served on
the federal grand jury that was supposed
to investigate the murrah building bombing
in Oklahoma city back in 1995.
Actually, the grand jury
has two responsibilities
that are outlined in this book.
The first one says,
"the grand jury operates
as a sword, authorizing the
government for prosecution
of suspected criminals
and also as a shield,
protecting citizens from unwanted
or inappropriate prosecutions."
That's not somethin' the
media or the government
ever points out, but that was actually
the reason for a grand
jury in the first place,
to protect citizens from the crown,
who at the time had the habit of
prosecuting their political enemies
or anybody they chose for any reason.
The grand jury, our grand jury
that was supposed to be calling witnesses,
were not allowed to call any.
And it was my letter to the judge,
tellin' him that and demandin' that we be
allowed to call witnesses,
that got me excused
from the grand jury.
What you will hear and
what they say that's a lie
is that the grand jury foreman
is the only one that has the right
to do this or that.
And that's not true,
according to the book.
Any member can demand anything he wants,
for any reason.
Can be just his personal opinion,
it can be from information he gets.
And of course, they tell us,
"you can't watch TV.
You can't read the
paper," that's nonsense.
That's nonsense.
Grand jurors need to be well-informed
if they're gonna do their job properly.
See, we were never allowed
to see the photo evidence
from the cameras on the murrah building
that would have shown
the truck being parked
and the people who got out of the truck,
that's all on tape.
And we were authorized to see all of that,
but we weren't allowed to see it.
And in fact, nobody's
been allowed to see it.
All those tapes have been kept under wraps
for 15 years.
It was just too important.
Just too important to the American people
to know what happened
there for me to keep quiet.
Because nobody else was gonna speak up.
The other grand jurors were petrified
because they observed on a daily basis
the kind of intimidation
tactics that were used
by the department of justice attorneys
to attempt to keep me under control.
And when they found out
about the FBI visits
to my home, that really shook 'em up.
Now they seem scared to talk to me
in the men's room.
Hoppy will never be silenced.
In 1998, he ran as an
independent candidate
for governor of Oklahoma,
intent on reopening
the investigation into the bombing.
After being excluded from
the gubernatorial debate,
hoppy walked on stage to ask
governor frank keating why.
I'll go up there
on the record as saying,
do you think I should participate.
You still believe that?
- Thank you, audience.
Mr. Jenkins, your follow-up now.
Two years after the bombing,
the trial of Tim McVeigh
began in Denver, Colorado.
The trial had been moved out of Oklahoma
despite the constitutional mandate
that federal crimes must be tried
in the district in which they occurred.
The truth seekers were assured that
all of their questions
would be answered in court.
- The trial was not handled appropriately,
it was handled in a way
that was very prejudiced
against the defendants.
If you look at what judge matsch did
concerning prejudicing the jury,
toward the people that
are being prosecuted by,
two weeks, he showed them
pictures of dead babies
and blood and guts, and
which is all basically,
in my understanding of the law, illegal
to prejudice the jury like that.
Yet, they did that kind of stuff,
apparently on purpose.
- I was told that by the U.S. attorney
that if I attended the trials in Denver,
that all of my questions
would be answered.
I gave up everything I had,
my apartment and everything,
and I moved to Denver.
And I attended both trials and by the time
Terry Nichols's trial was over,
I had more questions.
And no answers.
The trial lasted three weeks.
In contrast, the o.J.
Simpson trial in 1995
had lasted nine months.
The jury deliberated
for less than 24 hours,
and sentenced Tim McVeigh to death.
McVeigh waived all his appeals,
and was fast-tracked to be the first
federal prisoner executed in decades.
Just before his execution date,
the FBI announced that they had withheld
thousands of pages of documents
that could have influenced his trial,
which led to a month-long
stay of execution.
- I mean, they weren't
able to get thousands,
at least thousands, probably
a lot more than that,
of documents from, you know, the FBI
and the DOJ.
They just wouldn't turn them over.
On June 11, 2001,
Tim McVeigh was put to death
by lethal injection at
the federal death row
in terre haute, Indiana.
He left no message and
was quickly cremated
without an autopsy being
performed on his body,
contrary to the standard procedure
for executed prisoners.
Terry Nichols was tried and found guilty
in a separate trial, and
received a life sentence
without the possibility of parole.
In 2004, Terry Nichols
was then tried in Oklahoma
on state murder charges
in the prosecutors' hope
of imposing a death sentence.
Nichols was found guilty,
but a jury once again
refused to execute him.
- Those jurors did the best job they could
with the case that was presented to them.
I think what their
statement says is they knew
there was something wrong and somebody
had some involvement here.
They also, as they have said themselves,
that there were lies,
there were mistruths,
there were bungling, there was arrogance,
there was things that were not pursued,
like the other John does,
and so they felt like
there was a reasonable doubt.
Michael
fortier became a witness
for the federal prosecutors,
received a 10-year sentence,
and was released in 2006 directly into
the witness protection program.
Justice, the government announced,
had been served.
♪ And I know tomorrow ♪
Hey!
♪ Will be the same ♪
♪ 'cause we've got a life of love ♪
♪ that won't ever change ♪
♪ every day ♪
As the
government proclaimed justice
for all impacted by the bombing,
the people back in Oklahoma
still sought the truth,
and knew now they were on their own.
The list of questions continued to grow,
due to the mysterious death of
Oklahoma city police officer
sergeant Terrance yeakey.
Terry yeakey, unlike the rest of Oklahoma,
may have known too much.
- Officer yeakey was
just over 30 years old
at the time of the bombing.
The morning of the bombing,
he was issuing a traffic ticket
near the civic center music hall,
which is about four blocks to the west of
where the murrah building sits.
He dropped the ticket
book, let the woman go,
and says, "I have to,
obviously, attend other things,"
he heard the multiple blasts coming
from the murrah building.
Sped up there in his
Black and white squad car
and immediately started
pulling out the first
of eight people; Mr. Tom
hall being the first,
a former employee of the gsa.
Tom, to this day, in fact, I talked to him
a couple of weeks ago,
still has the utmost respect
for officer yeakey.
He literally saved his life.
Officer yeakey, being
an astute police officer
for seven years, veteran of
the Oklahoma city police department,
knew that something was horribly wrong.
He tried to get the official storyline out
through his commanding
officers at the Oklahoma city
police department, through his family,
through his ex-wife,
and he chose to withhold
some of the storyline
because he was in fear of
for his family and his wife
and his two young daughters at the time.
What we found out, between the hours
of eight A.M. and one P.M. that morning,
he was brutally murdered a mile and a half
from the front gate of
the El Reno penitentiary.
From that moment that his body was found,
we know that the crime
scene was destroyed.
There were spade shovels that were used
to turn over the crime scene,
ballistics, any gunpowder residue,
anything that had to do with his death
was completely destroyed,
it was corrupted.
- He started having problems
with, not only at work,
but his apartment got broke into,
his car got broke into, things were stolen
out of his house.
He had accumulated reports, evidence,
I don't know what all, but
he was going to take it
out to a mini storage in El Reno.
And he left one night,
and he told a friend of his
that they were gonna go out to dinner,
he says, "I gotta run
out and put some stuff
in mini storage and soon as I shake
these feds that are followin' me,
I'll be back and we'll go to dinner."
He never came back
instead, he was found the next day
by Canadian county sheriff's deputy.
Well, they found his car first,
and then they found him in a field
near the El Reno penitentiary.
The damage to his body was
obviously a torture homicide.
It was obvious.
But what intrigued me the most
that he had several cuts
on both of his wrists,
inside both elbows, both jugular veins.
He'd been beaten.
He had ligature marks around his neck,
he had handcuff marks on his hands,
on his wrists, and he had a small caliber
bullet wound that started above
on the right-hand side of his temple,
and exited low on his cheek,
with no powder burns.
- The day of his death,
when my daughter called me,
I left work, went to El Reno
to help because I could hear
the seriousness in her voice
that she was getting
upset, why would the police
be callin' her lookin' for Terrance?
And when we went to the apartment
where he lived, the
manager there stated to us,
"well, why are you lookin'
for him, the police
have already been here
and taken his cruiser."
I'm not sure what was goin' on,
it was strange.
At about 10 o'clock at night,
I had put my grandkids to bed.
The phone rang, and when
I picked the phone up,
I could hear my daughter
screamin' in the background.
And I assumed something bad had happened,
but I didn't think death.
And my son said, "mom, they found Terry.
He's dead."
- One of the things that surprised me was
that there was no autopsy performed.
The other thing that
really bothered me was
we were being told that Terry
was high on drugs and drunk.
And of course, the
medical examiner's office
did a report on Terry and his injuries,
which was really not an autopsy,
just an overview, and
it showed that his bac
was zero, meaning no
blood alcohol content.
There was no drugs in his system.
It bothered me that
they didn't treat Terry
like the police officer like he was.
He was a good guy.
- And he never said to
us that "I'm depressed."
You know, "I need help."
Not to me, or not to his sisters.
I think it's only fair that we know,
as Terrence's family
members, what happened.
- Officer yeakey's official
cause of death was suicide,
and that was actually laid out
on the medical examiner's report
at the Oklahoma state medical office,
examiner's office.
We've since were able
to retrieve that record.
What we found out though
is that number one,
the crime scene was corrupted,
went completely in the face
of proper investigative procedure.
The extent and the amount,
the number of wounds
on his body clearly shows that he was,
he couldn't commit suicide.
Physically and logistically,
you just can't do that
to yourself.
Terry also, we knew, was anemic.
He would not have been able to traverse
over half a mile from where his car was
to where his body was found,
and not have passed out,
his heart would have
literally given out, he wouldn't have had
enough blood pressure
in his body to survive.
The car was locked, the
windows were rolled up.
The keys were in the console.
There was a bloody knife in the glove box.
You don't stab yourself 13 times
and have superficial wounds on the,
along your arms and
chest and your upper neck
and walk a half a mile and decide to die
next a tree.
- Being the family of an officer,
I expected some kind of care
and consideration for us,
being the family of Terrance.
There was another detective
by the name of mullinex
that told my daughter that she looked at
too many movies and she needed to see
a psychiatrist, when we
were asking questions,
wanting to know about his belongings,
wanting to know about things that happened
during the course of where they say
they found my son.
And I don't think this
was very kind of them
and considerate of us, being family,
that they should have
talked to us like that.
But they did.
And as far as I'm concerned,
that made me more suspicious
of what happened to my son.
The brutal torture
and murder of Terry yeakey
served not only to silence his voice,
but the voices of other first responders,
who may have seen something
that would shed light
on what really happened.
Those who keep their silence
know exactly what Terry saw.
But he will never be forgotten
by those who ask questions
and demand answers.
In the absence of official action,
a group of concerned
citizens decided to form
their own investigative panel:
The okbic, better known as
the Oklahoma bombing
investigation committee.
Their goal was to compile enough evidence
that would attract attention by the media
and the government, and therefore compel
a more thorough investigation.
Entirely funded by donations
and their own money,
the okbic took affidavits,
recorded eyewitness testimony,
and paid for private investigators
to chase down leads.
- I'm Charles key, state representative
in Oklahoma city, and I've formed
the Oklahoma bombing
investigation committee.
I had a number of constituents come to me
and other people that started raising
their own questions
about the investigation,
what direction it was goin',
because it seemed like there was an effort
to try to change that initial report
of what took place on the
first day of the bombing
as the days and weeks went by.
- We looked at what state representative
Charles key did.
He went on the facts,
he went on the information
the grand jury gleaned,
and clearly there was
complete prior knowledge.
- I observed the fact that Charles key
seemed to be standing up for
the truth in some areas that I felt like
was not being dealt with appropriately
by authorities.
The Oklahoma bombing
investigation committee
was formed for one purpose and
that is to obtain the truth.
- First, I thought, "ah,
that's just another politician
trying to get a little publicity,"
then when I met them, met Charles key
and colonel Wallace, and Dale Phillips,
found out that they were for real,
and they asked me if I would join 'em.
And I agreed to join 'em.
- I think Charles key's work
is absolutely outstanding,
and it continues to be.
Even to this day, we're looking at
about 16 years on,
almost, coming this April,
Charles took a lot of risks.
- When we saw what was goin'
on with the investigation,
and that it was trying to move away from
the early facts that were presented
by law enforcement and by the media,
we pursued establishing
a county grand jury
in Oklahoma county.
Something unique to Oklahoma
and just a few other states in the country
that allow citizens' grand juries
to be impaneled to investigate
things such as this.
- The committee meetings
were very serious.
We fought the government at every level,
all the way through to the supreme court
of the state.
- We had a lot of people that came forward
and brought us a lot of information
that we wouldn't have
gotten any other way.
We were pursuing all the information
that we could get our hands on
about the bombing,
and we were trying to get a
congressional investigation
of the bombing.
- I was in awe at the amount of effort
that they put in in that first
six and a half years before
the book was released,
and then they have the book released,
come out to the general public
three weeks before 9/11 occurred.
And to see every single
obstacle that was thrown
in their face from, all
the way from the news media
to financial, to emotional,
and interviewing over 329
victims, family members,
and survivors, all these people
were consistently, basically saying,
"I am not going to fail,
I'm not gonna quit,
I want the truth to come out on this."
- So we formed the
Oklahoma county grand jury
to have essentially a
citizens' investigation
into the Oklahoma bombing,
and that caused us to have to get,
to gather a number of signatures
from citizens of Oklahoma county,
which we did.
- We got, I don't know,
11, 12,000 signatures.
We only required 5,000.
And by getting all those signatures,
getting them validated and everything,
we then got x amount of
money, a lot of money,
and the opportunity to
set up a grand jury.
Well, they turned the grand jury
over to our enemy,
which was Bob Macy,
and basically gave him the money,
and then he proceeded to investigate us.
- I wrote a letter to the
district attorney, Macy.
Told him what I had seen
and that I wanted to
testify in the grand jury.
I got a letter back from him
telling me that the grand jury
did not want to hear anything I had to say
about the bombing.
- After the Oklahoma county grand jury
was actually initially formed,
then there were some
efforts to try to stop that
by the Oklahoma county da and others.
And at that time,
we organized ourself in a more formal way.
We hired private investigators
and some others to help us
put the information that we
had gathered together in a form
that we could present to
that county grand jury.
- Four or five, six months
into the investigation,
we started suspecting
that our phones were tapped,
and I don't remember how
we got the information,
but there was, we were given
a number that we could dial
and it would either confirm or,
they were tapped or that they weren't.
And we dialed this number
and it would confirm it.
We didn't really have anything to hide,
so it didn't really make
that much difference.
It didn't affect our
investigation too much.
- I think as we finalized our
work as we got to the end,
as that grand jury was impaneled,
and as we put this report together,
we had a lot of media that
was waiting for this report.
They were ready to give it
some significant coverage,
and our report came back
from the book publisher
about two weeks before 9/11,
and one of the things that we said
and some others said
during that time frame,
as before and after 9/11,
that the reason that we did this
is because if you don't ask the questions
and you don't hold government accountable
in everything that it does,
not just bombings like
this, but everything,
then you'll have the same
mistakes happen again
and they will get worse as time goes on.
The official story dictated
that the Ryder truck
packed with 1,200 pounds of
ammonium nitrate fertilizer
and fuel oil, called anfo,
detonated on the northeast
side of the building
and was responsible for all the damage.
That hypothesis later evolved
into the 4,800 pounds of anfo,
then up to 7,000 pounds of fertilizer
and nitromethane?
In fact, the only consistent
theme of the official narrative
is its inconsistency.
- The truck bomb just
delivers an air blast.
That's all it does, it's
called an air blast.
But when you've got
eight-foot-thick columns
of concrete filled with rebar
the size of your arm,
an air blast probably
won't even break one.
It will break windows, that's about it,
but some of these columns were ripped up,
shredded, tossed around.
- Because a truck bomb is
gonna release its energy
simultaneously in every direction,
and so the damage pattern to the building
or whatever structure
it's parked in front of
and intending to blow
up, if it's a big enough,
big structure, bigger than
a truck bomb can take out,
the damage pattern's gonna
be roughly a semicircle.
- Now, I looked at the building,
I was on the bomb squad
for a couple of years,
I've worked some bombings,
and I looked at the building and I knew
that the damage done to that building
couldn't have come from
a truck with anfo in it.
- A blast does not turn corners,
and it did look like that
there was a secondary explosion
or a more intense explosion towards
the east side of the building.
The explosion, or that
portion of the explosion
did basically clear everything
from the front of the
building to the south wall.
The Oklahoma
bombing investigation committee
was presented with evidence
that explosives planted
inside the building were responsible
for the collapse and
most of the casualties.
In this rarely seen footage
taken by the Oklahoma
county sheriff's office
minutes after the bombing,
the north side parking
lot is shown littered
with paper and debris from
inside the murrah building.
How did this volume of
paper transport itself
against the blast wave of the truck bomb
and magically appear on the
other side of the street?
- And then we look at the fact
that you have bombs clearly
inside the building,
it's blown out across the street,
pieces of it on top of buildings
the opposite direction that
the rubble should have,
you know, gone in if there was truly
this high-powered truck bomb out front
that caused all the damage.
- And I can tell you that
the building was blown
from the inside because
all the debris was piled up
against the general electric building
clear across the parking lot.
In fact,
several witnesses report
that bombs were going off in the building
before the truck bomb exploded outside.
- The first thing that I experienced,
when I was sitting there
signin' some papers for Ruth,
I felt the building start shaking
and never had anything
like that happen before
and I just kind of froze,
and then the lights went out.
It didn't get totally dark
because the whole front
of the building was glass.
The lights went out and then the debris
started fallin' on my desk,
and then somethin' hit me
in the back of the head
and knocked me out before
the truck bomb went off.
What that tells you is that there were
other explosive devices in the building
that actually brought the building down.
- The building started
to sway back and forth,
it was going back and forth.
And I had sat there and I thought,
"no, it doesn't feel like an earthquake,"
and I was kind of stunned
and then about seven
or eight seconds later,
I felt this explosion, and you could feel,
actually feel the concrete floor
actually rising from underneath you.
You could feel it coming
up from the other side.
- It was like slow motion.
We crawled under
before the glass started coming
and everything that just,
it just seemed to,
seemed to roll in on us.
I thought it was an
earthquake when it started.
It was just a kind of a shake
and then everything
started going like this
and I dove under the desk and
then all the glass came in
and the ceilings came down and-
- three seismographs
at the university of Oklahoma,
the omniplex science museum,
and in Franklin, Oklahoma,
recorded a seismic event
lasting eight to 10 seconds
that "suggest the
possibility of two blasts."
There were two energetic spikes,
one was the truck bomb,
and the second spike
was explained away as air blast
pushing on the ground or falling debris.
But a representative of the
Oklahoma geological survey
stated for the record that this spike
was not the result of floors collapsing,
and that the last five
seconds of ground motion
did not have air blast associated with it.
The khobar towers bombing
in 1996 in Saudi Arabia
killed 19 U.S. airmen.
That bomb was several
times larger than the bombs
supposed to have been used in Oklahoma.
It left a huge 85-foot crater,
yet there was no major structural damage
on the simple slab building.
What happened in Oklahoma city
to cause the major horizontal
support beam to fail
and the complete failure of
these two series of columns
on the east side of the building?
This collapse was responsible
for most of the casualties.
The crater, when seen from above,
is offset from the major structural damage
in the building.
For some reason, the official story
has inflated the size of this crater.
- The bomb, at least I've
seen where the reports
from the different agencies
have said the bomb extended
from the cab to the tail of the truck.
And one other thing that
really bothers me about that is
is the rear axle on the truck
went down and collided with a car
in front of the regency tower
about a block and a half away.
The front axle of the
truck was hurled eastbound
and struck a parking meter
about a block and a half away
in front of the ymca building.
If a bomb was that big,
that that rear axle
would have been driven into the crater
instead of being split
apart, as they were.
And the truck bomb itself, to me,
had to be between the two axles.
It could not have been
over that real axle.
- I was surprised from
the, even the fema report
and the published reports
that nobody could determine
what the size of the crater was,
and that's one of the things I brought up
with the grand jury investigation
is that the crater was half the size
that they had proposed in the fema report.
The crater had a five-gallon
bucket sitting next to it
after they had it uncovered,
and you could extrapolate
from the size of that bucket
to the size of the hole
as to what size the crater was,
and it was approximately 16 feet across.
- August 24, 1970.
It was a Monday morning.
Karleton Armstrong, his brother Dwight
and two other perpetrators, Leo Burt
and one other individual
drove up to the side of the sterling hall,
it was a math research building.
Dow chemical had their offices there.
It was federal government
as well as the university
faculty that worked there.
And they had drove a Ford econoline Van
stolen from a math professor
laden with four metal drums,
50-gallon drums full of
ammonium nitrate and fuel oil.
The sterling
hall bombing consisted
of 2,000 pounds of anfo,
and it was set off right
next to the building.
The windows were blown in,
the facade was damaged,
but there was no structural damage.
In fact, the army math lab
was closed for only one day.
In Oklahoma city, a similar anfo bomb
detonated 15 feet away from
a much more robust structure
and inflicted massive structural damage.
- What that case did was it
set a, it was a bellwether.
It set a standard for
us to look at that says,
okay, if anfo was in fact
used in Oklahoma city,
why did it not have the characteristics
that, what occurred in Madison?
Furthermore, the
signature of an anfo explosion
is nitric oxide, a noxious gas.
- There was certainly no fertilizer bomb.
We know that because there
was no ammonia gas in the air.
In every other explosion, and they,
and some students blew up,
did make an ammonium nitrate bomb,
but everybody who rushed to that building
after that explosion
had to be hospitalized.
If you ever smelled ammonia strongly,
and you're talkin' about
goin' into a horse trailer
or something like it, that's not strong,
but that'll gag you.
It will sear your lungs.
I mean, everybody that
smelled that ammonia gas
after that ammonium nitrate
bomb at that university
had to be hospitalized.
It would have been 30 minutes or an hour,
depending on how hard
the wind was blowin',
before anybody could have even approached
the murrah building if there
had been an ammonium nitrate bomb.
- There were other search
and rescue personnel
that were down there immediately
from St. Anthony's hospital nearby,
as well as office employees
from the surrounding offices.
They would have approached the crime scene
and buckled over almost immediately,
vomiting violently, if there
was ammonium nitrate gas.
There wasn't.
- I was watching general partin,
the former head of air
force weapons development,
point out that the building was blown out,
that it wasn't the signature
of an ammonium nitrate fertilizer bomb,
that there had been a cover up.
The damaged murrah
building drew the attention
of retired general Benton k. Partin,
former director of the air
force armaments laboratory.
General partin spent his career
conducting bomb damage
analysis with explosives
for the military.
General partin came to Oklahoma city,
examined the available evidence,
and rendered a conclusion far different
than the story being pandered
by the government and media.
- I spent over 30 years in the air force.
Most of that was in
research and development.
I went to a two-year graduate program,
eight quarters of armament
engineering graduates.
It was the first course
that was ever set up.
And after that,
I worked at the ballistic
research laboratories
at aberdeen, which was
two years of hands-on work
designing, developing
containers for rod warheads,
for the bomarc vessel and
other weapons systems.
Well, the truck bomb, even
though it was fairly massive,
was somewhat removed from
some of the structures
that were damaged.
It clearly had some,
what you call brisance damage,
where the blast pressure was way above
what you would expect to get
from the truck at that distance.
Brisance damage
is that caused by an explosive
whose blast wave is powerful enough
to shatter and destroy
the material affected.
The problem with the failed
columns at the murrah building
is at that distance, the
air blast from an anfo bomb
would have been ten times less powerful
than what was needed to
dissolve the concrete
and cut the rebar.
Those columns, had they
failed due to air blast,
should have broken with
sharp chunks of concrete
connected by rebar,
not sheared off at critical points.
Brisance damage indicates
contact explosives
placed directly on the beams.
Even more perplexing is the total collapse
of column b3,
which caused the floors on the east side
to pancake onto one another.
The building was gutted to
within feet of the other side.
Column b4, closer to the truck bomb,
is completely intact.
Yet we are supposed to
believe that a blast wave
traveled through b4,
leaving the sheetrock almost untouched,
and completely destroyed
the column farther away.
And most of the front
columns were destroyed
when the supporting header beam failed,
but the cause of failure,
supposedly being air blast,
should have thrown it into the building.
Instead, it fell straight down and rolled
towards the crater.
General partin's report was conclusive:
The murrah federal
building was not destroyed
by one sole truck bomb.
A major factor in its destruction
appears to have been
detonation of explosives
carefully placed at
four critical junctures
on supporting columns within the building.
Many independent experts concurred
with the partin report.
Sam Cohen, inventor of the neutron bomb,
issued this statement,
"I believe that the demolitions
charges in the building,
that were placed inside at
certain key concrete columns,
did the primary damage to
the murrah federal building.
It would have been absolutely impossible,
and against the laws of nature,
for a truck full of fertilizer and oil
no matter how much was used
to bring the building down."
The FBI put all their weight
behind the lone bomber theory
and tailored the evidence
to fit that scenario.
Dr. Frederic whitehurst,
a supervisor at the FBI crime lab,
turned whistleblower over
the bureau's handling
of the evidence in the
Oklahoma city bombing.
- Release a report today
condemning the FBI crime lab
for mishandling evidence and
for slanting its analysis.
The report is expected
to specifically criticize
the lab's handling of the Oklahoma city
and world trade center bombing cases.
It was the allegations
of FBI whistleblower
Frederic whitehurst that
sparked that investigation.
Forced the resign,
Dr. Whitehurst testified
in Terry Nichols' trial
that a fellow FBI chemist
had changed his findings
and lied under oath
after meeting with federal prosecutors.
The office of the
inspector general, or oig,
investigated whitehurst's charges
and issued a report which concluded
that the FBI crime lab
had improperly identified
the characteristics of anfo,
the weight of the bomb,
the detonation system,
and even what kind of explosive was used.
- The Oklahoma city case
will get a lot of attention
because what the inspector general goes on
at some length to say in his analysis
of an agent testimony in
some of the pre-trial stages
is that one agent in particular
made sort of seat-of-the-pants estimates
about the Oklahoma city bomb,
but then couched them in his reports,
in his written reports,
as being the result of
scientific evidence.
- The FBI laboratory's billed
itself for many, many years
as the premier forensic
laboratory in the world.
The people that did the things they did
knew doggone well what they were doing.
The Wright
armament laboratory
at eglin air force base
conducted a series of explosive tests
to compare their data to
the bombing in Oklahoma.
The eglin test structure
was a simple, three-story
concrete slab building
with no support columns.
The engineers at eglin tried
to recreate the truck bomb
as McVeigh and the FBI
claimed it was constructed,
with 4,000 pounds of anfo
packed into a dozen barrels.
But they found that each barrel
acted as a separate bomb,
canceling out the explosive
force of each other
and pushing most of the blast upwards.
So they constructed a
single, more powerful bomb
and exploded it outside
the target building
to test the effects of air blast.
They found that their
weaker test structure
suffered less damage
from a more powerful bomb
than was supposedly used at Oklahoma city.
The report for the Wright laboratory
at eglin air force base concluded
"the damage at the murrah federal building
is not the result of
the truck bomb itself,
but rather due to other factors such
as locally placed charges
within the building."
The evidence is undeniable,
despite the pleas of the official story,
that the Ryder truck bomb
was not the sole cause
of destruction that day,
that there were bombs
placed inside the building
which caused the brunt of casualties
as floors collapsed on helpless victims.
- And the rescuers apparently
had to abandon the people
they were trying to rescue temporarily.
Now were you there
a minute ago when somebody yelled,
they thought they'd seen a second device?
- Yes, sir, we were in the,
close to the parkin' area
trying to recover a victim.
As rescuers desperately tried
to free the victims from the rubble,
several evacuations of the site,
due to reports of other
bombs, impeded these efforts.
- At some point, we got to the corner
of fifth and I believe it was Robinson,
right there are the corner
of the murrah building,
and we heard "second bomb."
Somebody yelled "second bomb."
I stopped, I turned around,
people were runnin' past me,
and I just kind of watched
what, what was unfolding.
Of course, never, nothing ever did happen.
The Oklahoma
highway patrol reported
that another explosive device was found.
The Oklahoma city fire
department confirmed that.
Defense department logs recorded
that a second bomb was disarmed,
a third bomb was evacuated.
- The explosive that
they disarmed last night
was even larger.
Who planted
these bombs and had access
to the murrah building before the bombing?
A deputy sheriff recorded this footage
during one of the evacuations.
Here, the atf is seen
pulling out several weapons
and blocks of what appear
to be plastic explosive.
Was this the source of the bomb scare,
or did this ordnance come
from an illegal armory
that witnesses report the atf
kept in the murrah building?
The atf denies they kept
any weapons or explosives
in the building.
- Day one, hour two of the bombing,
the most significant event that happened
is when they said they found
other bombs in the building.
The second most significant
event was the way
they moved everybody
back and held 'em back.
There were still people alive
trapped in the building,
but they came in with two trucks
and backed them up to the murrah building
and a bunch of these guys
dressed in blue jackets
with no letters on the back
started taking boxes of files out
and puttin' 'em on this truck.
- We were told by a blonde female agent
that there were files
so serious to the government
that until those files were relocated,
there would not be any recovery effort.
- If you remember the whitewater
investigation in Arkansas,
all the paperwork was stored
in the murrah building.
They had FBI agents over in the fields
to the west of the murrah
building pickin' up paper
almost all day long.
- And it was during this time that,
early in the investigation,
that I started receiving
some various phone calls.
One of them was a phone call
from little rock, Arkansas.
The guy said that he was a federal agent,
he was not an FBI agent, he was not atf,
but what he did say was
during their investigation
of the Clintons on all the drug running
that went through mena, Arkansas,
and, you know, lasater's ranch
and all of that stuff that
was going on at the time
during Iran-contra,
that those records, when
Clinton went to Washington,
were transferred from there
to the murrah building.
- Because of the additional bomb threats
or because the building was unstable
and the firefighters couldn't get to them,
so those are, a lot of
patients, I think, were lost
that could have been saved.
After rescue
and recovery had been halted,
the building was prepped for demolition
even though all the bodies
had not been recovered,
and despite the architect's
report that it could be rebuilt.
The investigative team from
the American society of civil engineers
was not allowed on site.
The defense lawyers for McVeigh
were able to visit the site one time,
but even then, they were not allowed
to view the crater.
- They were going to halt
it on the 29th of April,
they were gonna halt the recovery
and prepare the building to be imploded.
We went back in after the final demolition
to relocate two victims
that we knew that we had left
and a possibility of a third victim,
which we also located him.
I don't know why they were in such a rush.
Gsa was saying the building was unsafe
and needed to be brought down.
A month after the bombing,
the Alfred p. Murrah federal building
was completely demolished
with less than 200 pounds
of explosives.
The wreckage was buried under armed guard,
and one can only think
that certain officials
breathed a sigh of relief as
the outstanding counterpoint
to the official story
disappeared in a cloud of dust.
Tidbits of truth about
the Oklahoma city bombing
would often come from the
most unlikely of places.
Another strange and brutal murder,
at first seemingly
unrelated to the bombing,
would set the stage for some
of the most damning evidence
that the government was
withholding from the public.
- My name is Jesse trentadue.
I'm an attorney from salt lake city, Utah.
My brother Kenneth Michael trentadue
was murdered in the
federal transfer center
here in Oklahoma city in August of 1995.
Kenny had a hard life.
You know, I often thought about that,
and how he ended up the way he did.
He was an incredibly bright
man, an incredible athlete.
He set the national record in high school
for the two-mile run as a freshman.
Went into the service,
and like so many boys did
during the Vietnam war, they
come out heroin addicts.
He robbed banks, two banks
to support that habit.
He was caught and he pled guilty.
He went and did his time.
He was a very strong guy.
He wasn't very big but he was very tough.
He was easygoing,
but he wouldn't back down.
So if you pushed him,
you were gonna get a fight,
and it was a fight you were gonna lose.
We loved him and stood behind him,
and he was a good man.
Kenny was supposedly arrested
for a probation violation
and sent to Oklahoma city
at the transfer center
for a probation hearing.
We now know that that's crap.
I said to him, "Kenny, what,
what are you doing there?"
And he says, "well, they sent me back here
for a probation hearing."
And we talked about getting him a lawyer,
and the fact that we didn't
expect him to do more
than a couple months.
And so my mother called me at work,
it was about seven in the morning,
and told me that, and
I couldn't believe it,
and that Kenny had
supposedly killed himself,
'cause I had just spoken
with him the night before.
There's no way in hell he
would have killed himself.
This is not a guy who kills himself.
I mean, his life is the
best it's ever been.
I found out later that an
autopsy had already been done.
Now, the government,
the federal government
didn't want one done,
but the state of Oklahoma required one
for a death in incarceration.
So the federal government didn't know
that there was an autopsy done,
and did not want the autopsy done,
and the federal government went twice
to the medical examiner's office
asking to have Kenny cremated.
It took a week to get his
body released and home,
and I kept getting the run around
from the federal
government, and then finally
I just screamed in the phone one day,
"why don't you keep him?"
And when the body comes home,
it's totally made up
so you can't see the wounds.
He was beaten head to toe,
his skull was smashed in in three places.
The soles of his feet had been beaten.
You could see the fingerprint
bruises on his arm
where he'd been held.
His throat was cut
and he'd been strangled.
And the federal government said
it was a suicide by hanging.
When his body's turned over
to the medical examiner
two hours later, he's wearing
nothing but boxer shorts.
The government said they
don't know what happened
to the clothes.
They cleaned the cell that morning
so the medical examiner can't
do an examination of it,
and the medical examiner's
not allowed into the cell
for six months.
And when he finally is allowed in,
he does a test that's called luminol
that will reveal the presence of blood.
And Fred Jordan told
me that the cell lit up
like a Christmas tree.
The logbooks involving
my brother disappeared.
The ones that didn't disappear,
the pages from the logbooks are missing.
The crime scene photographs disappear.
The negatives of the crime
scene photographs disappear.
The video camera supposedly malfunctions.
Within an hour of death,
he'd consumed the equivalent
of 30 bottles of Coca-Cola,
and Dr. Jordan told me
that caffeine is used
in a lot of countries,
like third world countries,
to enhance pain under torture.
And he also told me that the beatings
on the soles of the feet
were indicative of torture.
And I believe it was the FBI.
I firmly believe that
for a lot of reasons now.
I didn't start out believing that.
I started out trusting them
until I could see what they were doing.
And they would come to
me asking for information
and then immediately go
and destroy the evidence,
threaten the witness,
do everything they could
to prevent the case
from being made a murder.
People were leaking me stuff.
They wanted me to know, they wouldn't,
didn't want me to know who they were.
Late December of '95, early January of '96
I get a phone call.
The person won't leave their name.
The person said, "your brother
was killed by the FBI."
They said, "it was an
interrogation that went bad."
It was a case of mistaken identity,
that he fit a profile of
people who were robbing banks
to get money to attack
the federal government.
Just before he was executed,
I get a message from Tim McVeigh,
and he told me, he said,
"when I saw your brother's picture
and heard what happened to him,
I wanted you to know that
I think the FBI killed him
because they thought he
was Richard Lee Guthrie."
Early on, the FBI
had investigated the possibility
that a string of bank robberies committed
by what the media dubbed
"the midwest bank robbers"
had financed the bombing.
Led by Peter langan and
Richard Lee Guthrie,
aka "wild bill," the
gang called themselves
the Aryan republican army.
The purpose of the robberies?
To finance a race war
within the United States.
Wild bill closely resembled
some of the John Doe number two sketches
and had a tattoo similar to
that reported by witnesses.
In an affidavit, Peter langan revealed
that a member of the ara
had admitted to liabilities
concerning the bombing.
Another member had threatened,
"we're going to get them.
We're gonna hit one of their buildings
during the middle of the day.
It's going to be a federal building."
Most of the ara was
arrested for bank robberies
soon after the bombing.
Peter langan offered
to provide information
about his co-conspirators'
relationship with McVeigh.
This offer was refused.
- Then I got a call from
a great guy, j.D. Cash.
He was a hunting and fishing reporter
at the mccurtain county
news in eastern Oklahoma.
He had friends that were
killed in the bombing,
and family, wounded.
And one day, he calls me up
and he says, "Jesse, can I talk to you?"
And I said, "well, sure, who are you?"
He says, "I'm j.D. Cash," and he says,
"I'm investigating the
bombing in Oklahoma."
And he said, "I'm interested
in your brother's death.
Can I ask you some
questions," and I said, "yes."
And j.D. Said, "well,
did he have any tattoos?"
And I said, "yes."
And he said, "what, and where?"
I said, "a dragon tattoo
on his left forearm."
J.d. Said, "oh my god."
He said, "are you setting
down," I said, "yeah."
He said, "lemme tell you this."
He said, "when your brother was picked up
and sent to Oklahoma,
the largest manhunt in American history
was in place for John Doe two."
We didn't start out to solve
the Oklahoma city bombing case,
we started out for justice for my brother.
But every lead, every trail,
every bit of important evidence,
has brought us to the
Oklahoma city bombing.
Now, the freedom of information act
is an act congress passes,
it says the government
is supposed to turn over
documents and information to you
that you request, unless
there's a good reason not to,
such as national security.
I bring the first foia suit,
saying I want all documents
showing a link between the FBI
and the southern poverty law center,
and the Oklahoma city bombing.
And the FBI comes back
and says there are no documents.
They didn't know that i'd
been leaked two teletypes
from FBI director Louis freeh,
then-director Louis freeh,
talking about elohim city,
talking about informants,
talking about the southern
poverty law center,
talking about the fact that
McVeigh had called elohim city
two days before the bombing,
asking for more help.
So I sue them, and they walk in the court,
and they tell the federal
judge there's no documents.
Well, I filed those, too.
The federal judge looks at 'em, he says,
"you go back, and you do a manual search,
and you bring everything
you find back in the court."
Well, then they come back
and plead with the judge,
and they say, "judge,
we promised anonymity,"
and if we have to
disclose these documents,
it will reveal their names,
and their lives will be in jeopardy."
German citizen
Andreas Carl strassmeir,
aka Andy the German, came to the U.S.
In the early '90s.
Professing Neo-Nazi beliefs,
he moved to elohim city,
becoming their chief of security.
He was reported by atf
informant Carol howe and others
to make threats about
bombing federal buildings
and assassinations of public officials.
It is known that McVeigh
called elohim city twice,
looking for the mysterious German,
when members of the ara
were living with strassmeir.
McVeigh also attempted
to reach Andy's attorney,
kirk lyons, by phone, in
the days before the bombing.
- We started looking at
strassmeir real hard,
and this guy didn't add up, either.
He was on special assignment,
and disappears and shows up
in elohim city, came in through Texas,
and was placed at elohim city.
Now, why elohim city, I
mean, nobody in Germany,
if I haven't heard of elohim city,
and I live in Oklahoma,
how's anybody in Germany
hear of this place?
Well, evidently, it was from
a lawyer named kirk lyons.
I start putting dots together.
I start finding out who these people are
and who they know, who they run with
and what their background
and what their history is.
And we create a picture from this.
We have strassmeir doing all
this paramilitary training,
takes over as chief of security of a place
that didn't need any security.
Tells 'em they need to
get rid of their shotguns
and deer rifles and buy
assault rifles and skss,
and aks, and stuff like this,
because they're gonna be the next waco.
Well, he scares 'em down there,
they don't know what to do.
So they start, you know, gearin' up for
the last days of the book of revelation.
- Strassmeir's an interesting character,
these documents we got from the court.
It's my understanding he's a
German intelligence officer.
He's, apparently, after the bombing,
taken out of the country
by a former CIA operative,
back to Germany.
His visa, as I understand had expired,
and no one picked him up,
and he was smuggled out
through Mexico, and back to Germany.
- I said "why wasn't Andy
strassmeir questioned?"
And one of the attorneys said,
"oh, we did question him."
I said, 'yeah, but you waited
until he got back to Germany,
and then you called him up
over the phone and asked him
did he have anything to
do with the bombing."
- In Tulsa, at lady godiva's,
which is a strip bar,
one of the strippers, named Shanti,
said that McVeigh, and strassmeir,
and several people had come
in a few days before the bombing,
and there was a Ryder truck
parked out in the parking lot.
- What we can say about
Timothy McVeigh's connections
to elohim city is that he
called there at least twice,
once on April 5th and once on April 17th,
that he checked into a motel
within miles from there,
that he received a speeding ticket
and that he also calls
outlying areas of elohim city
residents or acquaintances.
So, very briefly, those are
his provable connections
to elohim city.
The southern
poverty law center,
along with the FBI,
kept informants in elohim city.
One of these may have been strassmeir,
the supposed Neo-Nazi.
Known primarily for its work in litigating
against hate groups,
and its outspoken chief
counsel, Morris dees,
the splc has also become
an informal intelligence-gathering
arm of the FBI,
and now, the department
of homeland security.
They share the same interest
with the federal government
in suppressing what they
knew about prior knowledge.
- By the FBI's own admission,
there were at least
between four and six
informants at elohim city.
I don't know what the
population of elohim city is,
but it sounds like, whenever
three people get together
to talk about overthrowing the government,
two of 'em are working for the government.
Andy strassmeir's
roommate at elohim city
was Michael Brescia, a young
skinhead from Philadelphia
who was also a member of the ara.
He was later convicted for bank robbery,
and also bore a striking resemblance
to the John Doe number two sketches.
The FBI and the atf had something to hide
in eastern Oklahoma.
Was McVeigh in elohim city?
If so, what was he doing?
- My name's Josiah stone, and
I was on a spiritual journey.
I integrated quite
quickly into elohim city,
and I was able to identify with
their concept of life,
because I was looking
for some answers to my own life.
I saw Timothy McVeigh at elohim city
eight weeks prior to the
Oklahoma city bombing.
And I remember him distinctly,
because he has a distinct face.
But he was smilin', he was smilin',
he was happy as he could be.
These people were loaded for bear,
and they were ready,
and they meant business.
I believe the mindset at elohim city was,
they didn't give a damn whether they were
implicated in it or not.
- What was interesting, and I think no one
has paid any attention to it,
is that the CIA was involved
at elohim city.
Not only were they involved,
but they had the spy satellites,
the national geospatial
intelligence agency.
I'd never heard of 'em before,
they run the spy satellites.
They had them over elohim city.
I think one of the things
that may be most productive
to getting at the truth was the discovery
of an operation the FBI had in place
since about 1991 called
patcon, p-a-t-c-o-n.
It's short for patriot conspiracy.
It was an idea they had to
infiltrate every militia group,
every Neo-Nazi group, every group critical
of the government in the United States.
The plan, apparently,
was to put informants
in with all of these groups.
And I think elohim city
was a patcon operation.
I think McVeigh was
obviously involved in it.
Now, whether he was a target
or an operative, I don't know,
any more than I know whether
the government intended
to blow up the murrah building.
But they knew it was gonna happen,
and they knew McVeigh was gonna do it.
And they don't stop him.
As alleged
in David Hoffman's book,
"the Oklahoma city bombing
and the politics of terror,"
strassmeir first aroused
suspicion that he was
an undercover operative
when he was caught in Texas
entering a federal building
at night with a key code.
Did he have access to
the murrah building also?
- When we interviewed Jane
Graham, who was a survivor,
she said that when she went to work,
it was either the day
before or two days before,
I don't remember which,
she parked in the basement parking,
and when she got out of her
car, and was walking across
the parking garage, she
saw three guys down there
wearing coveralls and
placing putty on the columns,
and stringing wire between the putty.
Later, she picks out one of the guys
from photographs and says, "that's him,"
and it was Andreas strassmeir.
- Strassmeir was there
listening, going over the plans.
He was listening to everything, he was,
what they were talking
about, looking at place,
pointing to things, but
when they were talking,
whatever they happened to
finally be talking about,
and when I was looking at him,
at that point, then he left
and went over to the other
side of the building,
so I wouldn't keep watching him.
The second man that was there,
who appeared to be military,
he's the one that the man in
charge told to put the stuff
back in the car.
The second man, obviously,
was taking orders
form the first man, because
he had wire in his hands,
which I thought was telephone wire.
It's that real light color,
thin wire, and he also had
what appeared to be gray putty.
- Well, that's exactly how
you string composition c4
with det cord.
- And the details are chilling.
We'll also focus on surveillance cameras,
cameras that caught the bombing on tape,
and maybe the men behind the bombing.
News channel has new information tonight
that there is a chance
surveillance tapes could be
the smoking-gun evidence,
and we ask candid questions
in a rare face-to-face
meeting with atf officials
close to the investigation.
We learned that video collected
from downtown businesses
the morning of April 19th may someday
be played before a jury.
Officials won't say who or
what, exactly, is on the tape.
However, numerous sources have
confirmed the tapes exist,
and that they reveal more than one bomber.
- And I said, "I want two
other things from the FBI.
I want the tapes from
the surveillance cameras,
leading to the murrah building
on the day of the bombing,
on the different buildings
around the murrah building,
and I want the tapes from the cameras
on the murrah building."
Because I had received a
government document that said
surveillance cameras
show the bomb detonating
three minutes and six
seconds after the suspects
exited the truck.
Suspects, not one, plural.
The fight now is over those tapes.
They don't deny they exist, they just say,
"we can't find 'em."
Now, the notion that
this is the biggest crime
the bureau had ever investigated,
to that point in time,
the largest mass murder
in American history.
The two most important
pieces of evidence you have,
the arrest of McVeigh, and the videotape
showing McVeigh delivering the
bomb to the murrah building,
you can't find?
Incredible.
- The enhanced photo shows
a very distinct possibility
of a man standing behind that truck,
and the time-sequence camera
took additional photographs.
So will those additional photographs show
there was a man there?
Will they show that he was alone?
Will it show it was the
suspect, Tim McVeigh?
The additional photographs in the trial
should help point that out.
- I think one of the things
that stands out to me
is the fact that, during
that first morning,
while we were being held at bay
from doing any recovery work,
there were FBI agents, or at
least, men in FBI raid jackets,
dismantling the video cameras
off the side of the building.
- I'm Charlie Rose, i'm
with legend video transfer,
and the FBI had employed me
to duplicate a number of videos
for them, shortly after
the murrah bombing.
I was asked to duplicate
approximately 400 tapes
for the FBI.
We had two FBI agents in the office.
We had two studios set up for duplication,
and each FBI agent was
required to stay in the room
with each of us that were in that room.
Really didn't have the opportunity
to sit back and watch the videos.
There's probably a lot to
learn, you know, from the videos
that they saw.
Some of 'em are meaningless,
but others, you know,
could make some powerful impact
on what actually happened.
- The government will not release the film
that was in the video cameras
on the front of the building
that would show whether I
was accurate or not accurate.
- Of course, the other achilles heel
is the videotapes of the building itself,
from the different surveillance cameras,
that no one's seen.
If McVeigh was Lee Harvey
McVeigh, all by himself,
the lone nut with a truck,
then why don't they show us
the videotapes of the truck?
Show us the videotapes of him gettin' out,
or was there more than him in the truck?
- There were, like, 20,
22 films in the area
that were confiscated by the FBI
that would have shown the
truck bein' pulled up,
people gettin' out of the truck.
It would have shown what
was goin' on at the time
the explosions took place, and obviously,
they confiscated those,
and it doesn't take much
to figure out that the federal authorities
weren't trying to get to the truth,
they seemed to be covering up things.
- Their first objective
is to protect the agency.
Not to do what's right, not to do justice,
not to serve the American people.
It's to protect themselves.
And they will do anything,
anything, to do that.
Tim McVeigh
was honorably discharged
from the army three
years before the bombing,
leaving behind an
exemplary service record.
After a brief but
intense combat experience
in the persian Gulf war,
McVeigh tried out for the special forces.
He pronounced himself unable to continue
just a few days into the testing,
and returned to his unit
demoralized and, some say,
a changed man.
- Through being able to see
Timothy McVeigh's letters
to his defense team,
this is really behind-the-scenes stuff,
letters to his family,
the memos the defense team
writes, which detail his mood
from day to day.
Some of the medical reports,
while he's in prison,
which detail his thoughts.
On the one hand, you have the McVeigh
who's mad at the government,
on the other hand,
you have the McVeigh who
works for the government.
The defense team themselves
could never obtain
his full military records,
and that even though
they were ordered by a judge.
- Where does he turn up?
He turns up in buffalo, New York,
and while's he's up there,
he creates what's known
as a legend.
Now, a legend is when you go undercover,
or you get sheep-dipped.
Sheep-dipped means you
change your identity,
you change your, who you work for,
and become a new person.
Changes his personality up
there, and all of a sudden,
he's ranting and raving
about the Turner diaries,
and overthrowing the government,
and all this other nonsense,
to where they're goin'
"this guy's a wacko."
He works up there six
months and disappears.
Where do we find him again?
Going into militia meetings
and doing the same thing.
Making sure he's noticed.
- If you look at Lee Harvey
oswald and Tim McVeigh,
and other patsies, they're very similar.
They're in the military, they
have security clearances.
McVeigh wrote
a letter to his sister,
who turned it over to the
FBI, in which he admits
that he was selected out
of special forces training
to participate in covert operations,
to help run drugs to
fund these operations,
and to assassinate security risks.
Mere bravado, or was
McVeigh telling the truth?
- The FBI had put wiretaps
on the McVeigh family's phone
after the bombing,
and so, I'm reading this
conversation back and forth
between his mother and his sister.
There's actually a few
of these conversations
where they say, "we don't understand
why the FBI won't listen to us,
and why the media is reporting
that Timothy McVeigh
washed out, or dropped out,
of special forces."
They're saying, "no, we were told
that he was still active in the military,
and that he was working
on these covert missions."
- And he told his family,
he told many others,
Terry Nichols, who signed an affidavit,
that McVeigh believed he was
out there infiltrating militias
and right-wing groups, and
was preparing to set 'em up.
And then, of course, he later learned
that he was the guy that got set up.
If McVeigh was
working for the government,
what are we to make of the involvement
of Terry Nichols, the
only convicted accomplice?
- When Nichols had been convicted,
but not given the death penalty,
in federal court and in state court,
he could not be tried again.
He wrote to Attorney General,
then-Attorney General
John ashcroft and said,
"come and see me, come and see me,
and I'll tell you all about it."
In his
declaration, Nichols stated that
"crucial parts of this
terrorist attack remain hidden
from the American people,
especially the identities
of 'others unknown,' who
collaborated with McVeigh
in the bombing."
McVeigh told Nichols that
he had been recruited
to perform undercover missions
while in the U.S. army.
Always the good soldier,
McVeigh revealed only one name
in his chain of command: Larry potts,
assistant director of the
FBI, and the lead agent
on the Ruby Ridge catastrophe in 1992,
in which a U.S. marshal
and 14-year-old Sam Weaver
and his mother, Vicky Weaver, were killed.
Larry potts later played an active role
in the siege at waco.
McVeigh was angry at
potts for going off-script
and changing targets at the last minute.
Another telling clue is on Tim
McVeigh's death certificate.
Despite being officially out
of the military for nine years,
and having held many
different jobs since then,
his listed occupation was "U.S. army."
So why did Tim McVeigh take
the fall for his accomplices?
Perhaps the intervention
of a known psychological
warfare expert explains
his silence till the end.
- The record clearly
shows that Dr. Jolyon west
consulted Timothy McVeigh's defense team.
Dr. West had previously been
psychiatrist and consultant
for Patty hearst, sirhan
sirhan, and Jack Ruby.
- We know that jolyon
west was considered to be
the number-two mind control
expert in North America,
under only Dr. Ewen Cameron.
- Dr. West came under a lot of scrutiny
during his time as chief
of psychiatry at ucla
because he was proposing using prisoners,
the general community,
poor people, minorities,
as test subjects.
And then, west's career
continues to flourish
through the '80s, and he
continues his research
into hypnosis, branches out
into terrorism and cults,
even consulting, and later writing
about the waco massacre.
- Dr. John Smith, if
that's even his real name,
was the protégé of Dr. Jolyon west,
Mr. Mind control,
and he was McVeigh's doctor in prison.
Today, it's reported that he
is one of the head psychiatrists,
one of the head doctors,
at Guantanamo bay.
The fact that you've got the protégé
of one of the fathers
of modern mind control
now being the head of
psychiatry at Guantanamo bay,
which is an admitted
mind-control laboratory,
that's even mainstream news,
I mean, you couldn't make
this up in a spy novel.
Truth is always stranger than fiction,
and it's all hidden in plain view.
Was the bombing the product
of a sting gone out of control,
with McVeigh taking the blame for a series
of government failures?
- They kind of set up a sting operation,
it appears to me, that went bad.
They thought they would
stop you know, the efforts
of strassmeir, millar, and
others through elohim city.
- I eventually talked
to this senate staffer,
and he informed me that
the Oklahoma city bombing
was actually a sting
operation that went wrong,
and that the effort to cover it up
was because they were not able
to stop the sting operation.
- When it fell apart, in
that they weren't able
to stop it right before it took place
and proclaim to the public
how great they were,
so they could get new funding for the atf,
because the atf had lost
so much credibility,
due to the Randy Weaver situation.
- I don't know if anybody'll ever know.
I know my brother was killed.
I'm often asked why, why, why?
I know my brother was killed
for information he didn't have
about the bombing.
Why the people in the
murrah building were killed,
as I said, I don't know
if they intended it,
or it just got away from 'em.
God, I hate to think that
they did it on purpose.
Perhaps it
was a deliberate attack
by a criminal element in this government,
using the reins of power
to execute and cover up
their crime.
- In 2006, the American
behavioral scientist published
the whole journal on this concept
that's being developed
called a state crime against democracy,
scad, for short.
There's a recognition,
a growing recognition,
among academia that, oftentimes,
people have not pursued
culpability into elite crimes
for the fear of being called
a conspiracy theorist.
When there is a state
crime against the people,
what generally happens is that inquiries
into these crimes tend
to be highly controlled,
tightly framed, and be totally reliant
on agencies who stand to be
embarrassed by investigations.
- It's now been declassified
that the Gulf of tonkin in 1964,
to get the United States fully committed
into the Vietnam war, was a staged event,
and those lbj tapes have been released,
where, days before McNamara
is telling him on the phone
how they're going to stage the event
to get the United States into the war,
and what he would need to say
at those press conferences.
In early 1995, the entire United States
was politically awakening.
The population was angry about waco.
They were angry about the United States
losing its sovereignty, and
Bill Clinton trying to pass
anti-second amendment legislation.
The federal government was
forced to basically come in
and create a crisis so
they could demonize anyone
who thought the government
was too big or out of control.
In 1994 and 1995, the congress
had tried, unsuccessfully,
to pass their omnibus crime bill,
that expanded federal jurisdiction,
that went after the second amendment,
that was going to create all these new
federal agencies to spy
on the American people.
And that was one of the reasons
that Oklahoma and other states
were upset, they understood
this was totally unconstitutional,
and a huge federal overreach,
and it violated the 10th amendment.
But after the Oklahoma
city bombing tragedy,
suddenly, they were able to rename it
as the antiterrorism and
effective death penalty act,
and that was able to sell through.
- Well, I think one of
the things we'll be seeing
over the next few weeks and months
are new legislation, both to deal with
domestic groups and
international terrorism.
There's already one bill, the
omnibus terrorism act of 1995,
that's on the cards.
One of the dangers is that we
stepped a little bit too far,
and this bill is very controversial.
- We see amazing parallels
between Oklahoma city
and 9/11, and we see it also being used
as a mass-conditioning
tool to launch a new war.
In the case of Oklahoma
city, a war against
the American people, in the case of 9/11,
a war against the middle east,
and an invasion for resources.
- President Obama's chief
of staff, rahm Emanuel,
recently said that you can never
let a good crisis go to waste.
This an example of realpolitik.
Taken to its extreme,
we can quote the words
of Robert shapiro, former Clinton advisor
who recently wrote, in an editorial,
that the only thing that can
save the Obama administration
is another terror attack
like Oklahoma city or 9/11.
So they think of us as expendable.
They're willing to ride our ashes,
stand in our graves, to
preserve their position.
This is an example of the noble lie.
- And in the months and weeks building up
to the Oklahoma city
bombing, there was incredible
conditioning on the news.
"These people are scared
of the federal government.
They're terrorists,
they're gonna kill you,
they're gonna bomb you, you
watch, it's gonna happen."
And then, sure enough, it happened.
And then you look at the evidence,
and government and Black-op
fingerprints are all over it.
The establishment is gonna have trouble
in the future orchestrating
further atrocities
like Oklahoma city,
because the public is now really
getting wise to their tricks.
Oklahoma city is one of
the best examples we've got
where we can prove clearly
that the official story
is a fraud, that the
government was involved,
and is using it to
demonize good Americans.
April 19, 1995,
will live on in history
as a reminder that we must
all take an active role
in holding our leaders accountable.
Its legacy and lessons must
be rooted in truth, not myth.
The victims demand truth and justice.
We have all witnessed
firsthand the harsh reality
of a government's ability
to manifest its will
upon the people, and
it's up the the people
to deprive governments of
the power to commit crimes
and profit from the lies.
- It is every patriotic American's duty,
every man, woman, and
child's responsibility
to research the facts
contained in this film,
to verify for yourself that
this information is true,
and that the rabbit hole goes even deeper,
and then take action
to bring the criminals
that perpetrated this attack to justice.